Hatfield, Ernest I; Papers apap255
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Ernest I. Hatfield Papers
1949-1968
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap255
3.78 cubic ft.
The Ernest I. Hatfield Papers document Hatfield's service in the New York State Senate, where he served from 1948-1964, and the years immediately following. The collection includes correspondence, scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, speeches, and bills he introduced.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Ernest Hatfield initially donated his papers to Syracuse University in a series of deliveries from 1966-1970. In 2006, the papers were transferred to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Biographical Sketch
Ernest I. Hatfield was born in Mt. Pleasant, Westchester County, NY in 1890. He graduated from Westchester County schools and attended the Eastman-Gaines Business College in New York City. Hatfield worked in insurance and real estate, and was a farmer. A resident of Poughkeepsie, NY, Hatfield was a Republican member of the New York State Assembly (Dutchess County 2nd District 1943-1944, Dutchess County 1945-1947) and served as chairman of the Mortgage and Real Estate Committee, and on the Insurance and Public Service Committees.
He then ran for and won election to the New York State Senate representing the 33rd District from 1948-1954 and the 35th District from 1955-1964. While in the State Senate, Hatfield was chairman of the Banks Committee and served on the Agriculture, Education, Excise, Finance, Labor and Industry, Public Relief and Welfare, Public Service, and Rules Committees. In addition, Hatfield was chairman of the temporary New York State Commission on Historic Observances.
Hatfield also was a member of the Freemasons, Knights Templar, Grotto, Exchange Club and Common Council in Poughkeepsie. He owned the business E.I. Hatfield, Inc. He died in 1977 in Dutchess County.
Scope and Contents
Ernest Hatfield Papers donated his papers a few years after he left the New York State Senate. The collection contains correspondence, scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, photographs, printed bills, and legislative transcript materials mostly dating from 1950 to 1964 during his Senate service. A Republican, Hatfield represented the Dutchess County 33rd district from 1948-1954 and 35th district from 1955-1964 in the State Senate. Although he previously served in the New York State Assembly, the collection does not include materials from this tenure. Topics of interest in the collection include documents related to Hatfield's role as chairman of the New York State Commission on Historic Observances and the Social Security bill, which prevented the separation of Social Security from the pensions of retired civil service employees.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - General Correspondence, 1953-1968
Series 2 - Legislative and Public Affairs, 1950-1951, 1954-1957, 1959-1964, 1967, Undated
Series 3 - Scrapbooks, 1949-1964
Series 1 and 3 are arranged chronologically. Series 2 is arranged alphabetically by the subject of the legislative bills.
Politics and Politicians; Politicians--New York (State); New York (State)--Politics and government; Dutchess County (N.Y.); Poughkeepsie (N.Y.); Bills (legislative records); Clippings; Correspondence; Files by subject; Legislative Records; Scrapbooks; Hatfield, Ernest I.; New York (State). Legislature. Senate; New York (State). Committee to Revise Banking Law, Joint Legislative; New York (State). Temporary State Commission on Historic Observances; New York (State). Legislature. Senate. Committee on Finance; New York (State). Legislature. Senate. Standing Committee on Labor and Industry; New York (State). Legislature. Senate. Standing Committee on Agriculture
- General Correspondence, 1953; 1955-1968; 1; 0.5 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence, newspapers clippings, and memos directed to Ernest Hatfield from fellow government officials and constituents. Subjects vary from casual greetings and congratulatory messages to individuals asking for help obtaining birth certificates or clarifying their pension issue.
  - Correspondence, 1953; 1955 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 2-5)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 10-12)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1964-1968 (Box 1 (1-General Correspondence), Folder 14)
- Legislative and Public Affairs, 1950-1951; 1954-1957; 1959-1964; 1967; Undated; 2; .8 cu. ft.
  Arranged alphabetically by the subject of the legislative bill.
  This series contains bills introduced by Ernest Hatfield or ones he wanted to amend, correspondence related to bills, the State Commission on Historic Observances Historic Observances and related correspondence, and legislative transcripts. Items that may be of interest to researchers are Hatfield's attempts to raise funds and garner support to build the Beacon-Newburgh Bridge, the Chiropractor bill which supported recognizing the chiropractic profession, and the Social Security bill in the Civil Service Law which opposed the government in separating Social Security benefits from pension of retired civil service employees.
  - Agriculture and markets law, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 15)
  - Alcoholic beverage control law, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 16)
  - Amend previous acts, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 17)
  - Blatnick bill, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 18)
  - Chiropractor bill, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 19)
  - Civil Service Law, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 20)
  - Compulsory automobile insurance bill, 1954; 1962-1963 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 21)
  - Compulsory workman's compensation insurance for farmers, 1964 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 22)
  - Concurrent resolution of Senate and Assembly, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 23)
  - Conservation law, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 24)
  - Correction law, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 25)
  - County law, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 26)
  - Dirksen Eastland bill, 1964 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 27)
  - Education laws, 1955-1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 28)
  - Erwin bill, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 29)
  - Firearm bill, 1964 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 30)
  - General business law, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 31)
  - General municipal law, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 32)
  - Greenport Fire District, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 33)
  - Hatfield election materials, Undated (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 34)
  - Highway law, 1956; 1967 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 35)
  - Insurance law, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 36)
  - Joint Legislative Committee on docks in the City of New York, 1962 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 37)
  - Joint Legislative Committee to Revise the Banking Law questionnaire, 1962; Undated (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 38)
  - Judiciary law, 1955; 1966 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 39)
  - Labor laws, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 40)
  - Legislative primer, 1959 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 41)
  - Legislative report from Senator Hatfield, 1964 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 42)
  - Local finance law, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 43)
  - McCarthy amendment, 1964 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 44)
  - McNeil Mitchell bill, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 45)
  - Metcalf Baker Bill, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 46)
  - New York State Commission on Historic Observances, 1958-1960; 1964-1965 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 47)
  - New York State Commission on Historic Observances booklets, 1960 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 48)
  - Penal law, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 49)
  - Pension of retired public employees, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 50)
  - Poughkeepsie Armory employee bill, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 51)
  - Prohibit state/public corp to restrict representation of employee, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 52)
  - Public authority law, 1956-1957 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 53)
  - Randall bill, 1964 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 54)
  - Real property law, 1955-1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 55)
  - Receipt and fulfillment of requests for copies of legislation, 1955-1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 56)
  - Retirement and Social Security law, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 57)
  - Savings bank branch bill, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 58)
  - Senate Bill No. 3116, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 59)
  - Senate Bill Introduction No. 3423, Print No.3781, 1964 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 60)
  - Senate Introductory 2095, 1964 (Box 1 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 61)
  - Social welfare law, 1956 (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 1)
  - Speeches and related correspondence, 1950-1951; 1956-1957; 1960-1963; Undated (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 2)
  - Standing Committees of the Senate, 1956 (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 3)
  - State finance law, 1956 (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 4)
  - State laws, 1956 (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 5)
  - Suffolk County bill, 1956 (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 6)
  - Taconic State Police, 1956 (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 7)
  - Tax law, 1956 (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 8)
  - Town law, 1956 (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 9)
  - Transcript of proceedings of the Joint Legislative Committee to Revise the Banking Law, 1963 January 30 (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 10)
  - Transcript of proceedings of the Joint Legislative Committee to Revise the Banking Law, 1963 January 31 (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 11)
  - Workmen's compensation law, 1956 (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 12)
  - Vehicle and traffic law, 1956 (Box 2 (2-Legislative and Public Affairs), Folder 13)
- Scrapbooks, 1949-1964; 3; 3.65 cu. ft.
  This series contains bound and unbound scrapbooks filled with newspaper clippings. Ernest Hatfield created the books which mention him in the articles, discuss events he attended, describe bills that he supported and the reactions to the bills, and other clippings that were of political interest to him.
  - Newspaper clippings, 1949 (Box 2 (3-Scrapbooks), Folder 14)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1950 (Box 2 (3-Scrapbooks), Folder 15-16)
  - Scrapbook, 1950 December-1963 September (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1955 January-1956 February (Oversized 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook, 1956 February-1956 March (Oversized 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1956 December-1958 April (Oversized 3, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1958 January-1958 July (Oversized 4, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1960 December-1963 April (Oversized 3, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook, 1963 October-1964 May (Oversized 5, Folder 1)